- number: 1
  question: 'Where the refuelling equipment is not mobile, the Civil Aviation 
    Orders require that an aeroplane being refulled shall:'
  answers:
    a: 'have no persons on board.'
    b: 'have a fire extinguiser on board.'
    c: 'have all electrical systems switched off.'
    d: 'be so placed that it can rapidly be moved to a place of safety if needed.'
  points: 1
- number: 2
  question: 'An aeroplane\'s fuel must be checked for presence of water:'
  answers:
    a: 'prior to every flight.'
    b: 'prior to the first flight of the day and at each change of pilots.'
    c: 'prior to the first flight of the day and following each refuelling.'
    d: 'after each refuelling and/or change of pilots.'
  points: 1
- number: 3
  question: 'Following an incident (a reportable matter), it shall be reported:'
  answers:
    a: 'within 72 hours, in writing for an RRM.'
    b: 'immediately by telephone for an IRM -- followed by a report in writing 
      within 72 hours.'
    c: 'Either of the above, as appropriate.'
  points: 1
- number: 4
  question: 'Which of the following would justify a Mayday call?'
  answers:
    a: 'You need navigational assistance.'
    b: 'You sight a capsized yacht off the coast.'
    c: 'A passenger becomes ill and you need to land for medical assistance.'
    d: 'You have an engine failure on a training flight.'
  points: 1
- number: 5
  question: 'An aeroplane must not fly over populated area at a height lower than:'
  answers:
    a: '1,500 ft AMSL.'
    b: '1,000 ft on the area QNH.'
    c: '1,000 ft AGL.'
    d: '500 ft AGL.'
  points: 1
- number: 6
  question: 'Increasing power when flying straight and level at cruise speed 
    will cause:'
  answers:
    a: 'an increase in airspeed and a decrease in drag.'
    b: 'an increase in airspeed and an increase in drag.'
    c: 'a decrease in airspeed and a decrease in drag.'
    d: 'a decrease in airspeed and an increase in drag.'
  points: 1
- number: 7
  question: 'What is the effect of lowering full flap?'
  answers:
    a: 'An increase in lift and a decrease in drag.'
    b: 'A decrease in lift and a decrease in drag.'
    c: 'A decrease in lift and an increase in drag.'
    d: 'An increase in lift and an increase in drag.'
  points: 1
- number: 8
  question: 'Stalling speed is increased if:'
  answers:
    a: 'weight is increased.'
    b: 'weight is decreased.'
    c: 'load factor is increased.'
    d: 'angle of attack is increased.'
  points: 1
- number: 9
  question: 'What do we call the angle between the chord line of an aerofoil 
    and the relative airflow?'
  answers:
    a: 'Angle of incidence.'
    b: 'Stalling angle'
    c: 'Sweepback.'
    d: 'Angle of attack.'
  points: 1
- number: 10
  question: 'Increasing the load factor will:'
  answers:
    a: 'decrease the stalling speed.'
    b: 'increase the stalling speed.'
    c: 'increase the stalling angle.'
    d: 'decrease the stalling angle.'
  points: 1
- number: 11
  question: 'What happens to lift and drag as the angle of attack approaches 
    the stalling angle?'
  answers:
    a: 'Lift increases and drag increases'
    b: 'Lift increases and drag decreases'
    c: 'Lift decreases and drag decreases'
    d: 'Lift decreases and drag increases'
  points: 1
- number: 12
  question: 'An aeroplane is descending at the best gliding speed. Raising the 
    nose will:'
  answers:
    a: 'increase the gliding range.'
    b: 'decrease the gliding range.'
    c: 'decrease the gliding angle.'
    d: 'decrease the rate of descent.'
  points: 1
- number: 13
  question: 'When compared to the stall IAS at 1,000 ft, the stall IAS at 
    10,000 ft will:'
  answers:
    a: 'increase by approximately 40%.'
    b: 'decrease by approximately 40%.'
    c: 'be the same.'
    d: 'vary according to the actual density at 10,000 ft.'
  points: 1
- number: 14
  question: 'If a tailwind is encountered during a glide descent, when compared 
    with a glide in still-air conditions, the:'
  answers:
    a: 'aeroplane pitch angle will be shallower.'
    b: 'flightpath over ground will be steeper.'
    c: 'distance over ground will be greater.'
    d: 'rate of decent will be less.'
  points: 1
- number: 15
  question: 'When in a 30 degree banked level turn, the load factor:'
  answers:
    a: 'is the same as in straight an level flight.'
    b: 'decreases by a factor of 15%.'
    c: 'will increase to 1.15g.'
    d: 'will be limited by the airspeed.'
  points: 1
- number: 16
  question: 'What are the VMC requirements for a VFR flight conducted in Class G 
    airspace between 3,000 fg AMSL (or 1,000 ft AGL if higher) and 10,000 ft AMSL?'
  answers:
    a: 'Visibility 5 km, clear of cloud.'
    b: 'Visibility 8 km, 1,000 metre horizontally from cloud, 1,000 ft above or 
      below cloud.'
    c: 'Visibility 5,000 metres, 1,500 metres horizontally from cloud, 1,000 ft 
      vertically from cloud.'
    d: 'Visibility 8,000 metres, clear of cloud.'
  points: 1
- number: 17
  question: 'A cold front is likely to produce:'
  answers:
    a: 'cumiliform clouds with smooth flying conditions.'
    b: 'stratiform clouds with smooth flying conditions.'
    c: 'cumiliform clouds with turbulent flying conditions.'
    d: 'stratiform clouds with turbulent conditions.'
  points: 1
- number: 18
  question: 'The term INTER on a forecast means that the weather will be:'
  answers:
    a: 'interminable in nature.'
    b: 'expected to last for at least 60 minutes.'
    c: 'interrupted every 30 minutes.'
    d: 'expected to last for less than 30 minutes.'
  points: 1
- number: 19
  question: 'The cloud base in a TAF is given as height above:'
  answers:
    a: 'the 1013.2 hPa level.'
    b: 'the highest ground within 10 km of the aerodrome.'
    c: 'mean sea level.'
    d: 'aerodrome level.'
  points: 1
- number: 20
  question: 'The wind direction in the ATIS is given in:'
  answers:
    a: 'degrees true from the wind direction.'
    b: 'degrees magnetic to the wind direction.'
    c: 'degrees magnetic from the wind direction.'
    d: 'devrees true to the wind direction.'
  points: 1
- number: 21
  question: 'Using your navigation computer, determine the true airspeed (TAS) 
    if you are flying at 120 kt IAS, with temperature +15\u00B0C and a pressure altitude 
    of 8,000 ft.'
  answers:
    a: '139 kt'
    b: '132 kt'
    c: '127 kt'
    d: '120 kt'
  points: 1
- number: 22
  question: 'If the time in Sydney on 23 March is 0628 EST, what is the UTC time?'
  answers:
    a: '231628 UTC'
    b: '222028 UTC'
    c: '232028 UTC'
    d: '221628 UTC'
  points: 1
- number: 23
  question: 'The track to your training area is 270\u00B0M. If the wind is from 
    the south and is causing 10\u00B0 of drift, your heading would be closes to:'
  answers:
    a: '270\u00B0T'
    b: '280\u00B0M'
    c: '290\u00B0T'
    d: '260\u00B0M'
  points: 1
- number: 24
  question: 'Magnetic variation is:'
  answers:
    a: 'the angular difference between magnetic north and compass north.'
    b: 'the direction in which all compass errors occur.'
    c: 'always expressed in degrees, either East or West.'
    d: 'the angular difference between true north and compass north.'
  points: 1
- number: 25
  question: 'A line of longitude on a WAC is:'
  answers:
    a: 'drawn north-south and represents true north and true south.'
    b: 'drawn east-west and represents magnetic north and magnetic south.'
    c: 'sometimes referred to as isogonal.'
    d: 'drawn parallel to the next meridian.'
  points: 1
- number: 26
  question: 'On a day when the temperature is 30\u00B0C and the relative humidity 
    is 30%, carburettor ice:'
  answers:
    a: 'is unlikely to form.'
    b: 'will form with maximum power set.'
    c: 'is likely to form with cruise power set.'
    d: 'is highly likely to form with low power set.'
  points: 1
- number: 27
  question: 'Why do most aeroplane piston engines have dual ignition systems?'
  answers:
    a: 'For the sole reason of safety in the even of the failure of one magneto.'
    b: 'For safety and improved combustion.'
    c: 'For improved combustion even though safety is not increased.'
    d: 'To spread the load between each of the spark plugs in a cylinder.'
  points: 1
- number: 28
  question: 'If, following combustion, there is unburned fuel remaining in the 
    cylinders, then the mixture is described as:'
  answers:
    a: 'rich.'
    b: 'chemically correct for the power setting being used.'
    c: 'lean.'
    d: 'having a fuel/air ratio of 100%.'
  points: 1
- number: 29
  question: 'What do we call explosive, spontaneous combustion in the cylinders?'
  answers:
    a: 'Run-on.'
    b: 'Detonation.'
    c: 'Pre-ignition.'
    d: 'Normal combustion.'
  points: 1
- number: 30
  question: 'What is one effect of carburettor heat?'
  answers:
    a: 'It will result in more air immediately going through the carburettor.'
    b: 'It will not affect the fuel-air mixture.'
    c: 'It will enrich the mixture.'
    d: 'It will lean the mixture.'
  points: 1
- number: 31
  question: 'Which flight instrument gives a pilot a direct reading of the bank angle?'
  answers:
    a: 'Direction indicator.'
    b: 'Attitude indicator.'
    c: 'Turn coordinator.'
    d: 'Magnetic compass.'
  points: 1
- number: 32
  question: 'You are cruising in an aeroplane with a fixed-pitch propeller and notice 
    a slight drop in engine RPM. You suspect carburettor icing and apply full 
    carburettor heat. Which one of the following statements most correctly indicates 
    that ice was present?'
  answers:
    a: 'There will be an immediate increase in engine rpm as soon as the carburettor 
      heat is applied.'
    b: 'The engine will start to run roughly with a further decrease in engine rpm.'
    c: 'The engine rpm will remain constant.'
    d: 'The engine rpm will decrease and then increase.'
  points: 1
- number: 33
  question: 'When compared with an engine fitted with a carburettor, which of the 
    following applies to a fuel-injected engine?'
  answers:
    a: 'It is more prone to starting problems and is less susceptible to fuel 
      contamination.'
    b: 'It is easier to start when hot and is more responsive to throttle movement.'
    c: 'It is less likely to have icing problems and is more efficient.'
    d: 'It requires greater care in throttle handling and is more susceptible to 
      fuel contamination.'
  points: 1
- number: 34
  question: 'Fuel that appears to be uncoloured or very pale yellow is:'
  answers:
    a: '100 LL low-lead AVGAS for piston engines.'
    b: '100/130 AVGAS for piston engines.'
    c: 'MOGAS.'
    d: 'AVTUR (kerosene) for turbine engines (i.e. jet or prop-jet engines).'
  points: 1
- number: 35
  question: 'To improve engine cooling during maximum power climb, you should:'
  answers:
    a: 'fly at a higher IAS.'
    b: 'fly at a lower IAS.'
    c: 'lean the fuel-air mixture.'
    d: 'apply carburettor heat.'
  points: 1
- number: 36
  question: 'The correct sequence of the various strokes in a four-stroke engine is:'
  answers:
    a: 'intake, compression, power, exhaust.'
    b: 'intake, exhaust, power, compression.'
    c: 'intake, power, compression, exhaust.'
    d: 'intake, power, exhaust, compression.'
  points: 1
- number: 37
  question: 'Which statement concerning carburettor ice do you consider most accurate?'
  answers:
    a: 'Carburettor ice is most likely to form when the air temperature is in the 
      range -10\u00B0C to +20\u00B0C with visible moisture or high humidity.'
    b: 'The carburettor heater is a de-icing device that heats the air after it 
      leaves the carburettor.'
    c: 'Carburettor ice will always form when the temperature is below freezing.'
    d: 'The first indication of carburettor icing in an aeroplane with a fixed-pitch 
      propeller is an increase in rpm.'
  points: 1
- number: 38
  question: 'If the static vent ices over during descent, the airspeed indicator 
    will then read:'
  answers:
    a: 'zero.'
    b: 'higher than actual IAS.'
    c: 'lower than actual IAS.'
    d: 'correctly.'
  points: 1
- number: 39
  question: 'With battery and generator switches ON, what is the probable reason 
    for a zero reading on a left-zero ammeter?'
  answers:
    a: 'The battery is fully charged.'
    b: 'The alternator is still charging the battery.'
    c: 'The battery is completely flat.'
    d: 'The alternator has failed.'
  points: 1
- number: 40
  question: 'The pitot-static system supplies pressure for:'
  answers:
    a: 'the ASI only.'
    b: 'the ASI, artificial horizon, and VSI.'
    c: 'the ASI, turn and slip indicator and altimeter.'
    d: 'the ASI, VSI and altimeter.'
  points: 1
- number: 41
  question: 'If you decide to fly when you have a cold or flu, you put yourself at 
    risk of:'
  answers:
    a: 'being too tired to concentrate.'
    b: 'having balance difficulties and sinus pain.'
    c: 'becoming dehydrated.'
    d: 'developing hypoxia.'
  points: 1
- number: 42
  question: 'Atmospheric pressure variations affect the human body. These pressure 
    changes are:'
  answers:
    a: 'minimum at low level so we generally don\'t need to worry about them.'
    b: 'minimum at high altitude.'
    c: 'maximum at high altitude so we need pressurisation and oxygen supplied.'
    d: 'maximum at low level so we need to understand their adverse effects.'
  points: 1
- number: 43
  question: 'Which of the following drugs are considered acceptable for flying?'
  answers:
    a: 'Antibiotics.'
    b: 'Analgesics.'
    c: 'Antihistamines.'
    d: 'Amphetamines.'
    e: 'None of the above.'
  points: 1
- number: 44
  question: 'If an aeroplane is loaded in such a way that the centre of gravity is 
    outside the forward limit, it will:'
  answers:
    a: 'be very unstable longitudinally.'
    b: 'have a very short momentum arm.'
    c: 'be very unstable about the normal axis.'
    d: 'be very nose-heavy and difficult to rotate on take-off.'
  points: 1
- number: 45
  question: 'Along which axis of the aeroplane is the centre of gravity computed?'
  answers:
    a: 'Laternal.'
    b: 'Normal.'
    c: 'Longitudinal.'
    d: 'All of the above.'
  points: 1
- number: 46
  question: 'An aeroplane must not be operated at a weight in excess of the maximum 
    certified gross weight because:'
  answers:
    a: 'structural limitations will be exceeded.'
    b: 'an overloaded airplane is excessively stable in flight.'
    c: 'flight in excess of certificated weights is not possible.'
    d: 'fuel consumption will be greater.'
  points: 1
- number: 47
  question: 'Which of the following factors improves take-off performance?'
  answers:
    a: 'The runway sloping upwards.'
    b: 'A tailwind.'
    c: 'A crosswind.'
    d: 'Low atmospheric pressure.'
    e: 'Low atmospheric temperature.'
  points: 1
- number: 48
  question: 'V_NO is defined as the:'
  answers:
    a: 'maximum indicated airspeed for extended flaps.'
    b: 'true airspeed beyond which flight is not permitted.'
    c: 'maximum indicated airspeed for normal operations in smooth conditions.'
    d: 'indicated airspeed beyond which flight is not permitted.'
  points: 1
- number: 49
  question: 'Strong wake turbulance produced by wingtip vortices is most likely to form:'
  answers:
    a: 'behind a heavy aeroplane which is flying slowly just after take-off.'
    b: 'behind any aeroplane which is flying slowly and with full flap extended.'
    c: 'behind any aeroplane with is flying at high speed.'
    d: 'only behind aeroplanes powered by turbo-jet engines.'
  points: 1
- number: 50
  question: 'As you approach to land the wind is gusting. You increase your approach 
    speed by 5 kt to ensure a margin of safety. This means:'
  answers:
    a: 'the approach path flown will be steeper.'
    b: 'climbing for a go-around will not be possible.'
    c: 'the LDR will be greater.'
    d: 'descent will be much more rapid.'
  points: 1
- number: 51
  question: 'To load an aeroplane, where would you find the weight and balance 
    details for the aircraft?'
  answers:
    a: 'In the maintenance release.'
    b: 'On the passenger manifest.'
    c: 'In your flight instructors handbook.'
    d: 'In the aircraft flight manual.'
  points: 1
- number: 52
  question: 'The weight of 230 litres of AVGAS is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: '128 kg'
    b: '145 kg'
    c: '163 kg'
    d: '172 kg'
    e: '180 kg'
  points: 1
- number: 53
  question: '
  Use "Load System Charlie", p358. \n
  \n
  Given: \n
  EW 695 kg \n
  IU 19,788 \n
  The student pilot weighs 60 kg and the instructor weighs 75 kg. \n
  \n
  The maximum amount of fuel on board that will allow "utility category" operations immediately after take-off is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: '62 litres'
    b: '88 litres'
    c: '100 litres'
    d: '123 litres'
    e: '135 litres'
  points: 3
- number: 54
  question: '
  Use "Load System Charlie", p358. \n
  \n
  Given: \n
  EW 695 kg \n
  IU 19,788 \n
  The student pilot weighs 60 kg and the instructor weighs 75 kg. \n
  \n
  Load the aircraft with 95 kg weight of baggage and load 170 litres of fuel.\n
  The zero fuel weight condition is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: 'weight 824 kg, arm 2,821 mm'
    b: 'weight 890 kg, arm 2,933 mm'
    c: 'weight 932 kg, arm 2,960 mm'
    d: 'weight 990 kg, arm 3,004 mm'
  points: 2
- number: 55
  question: '
  Use "Load System Charlie", p358. \n
  \n
  Given: \n
  EW 695 kg \n
  IU 19,788 \n
  The student pilot weighs 60 kg and the instructor weighs 75 kg. \n
  \n
  Load the aircraft with 95 kg weight of baggage and load 170 litres of fuel.\n
  The take-off conditions is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: 'weight 932 kg, arm 2,960 mm'
    b: 'weight 1,013 kg, arm 2,999 mm'
    c: 'weight 1,035 kg, arm 3,004 mm'
    d: 'weight 1,053 kg, arm 2,960 mm'
    e: 'weight 1,102 kg, arm 2,999 mm'
  points: 2
- number: 56
  question: 'Use the following data\n
  Airfield:\n
    Elevation: 1,890 ft\n
    Runways: 17/35 sealed TODA 3,000 metres (slope level)\n
    12/30 short grass TODA 1,000 metres (slope 1% down to SE)\n
  ATIS:\n
    Terminal Information Delta\n
    Runway 12\n
    Wind 150/15\n
    QNK 1,010
    Temperature 15\u00B0C\n
    Cloud: FEW 3000\n
    Runway wet.\n
    Works in progress Runway 17/35\n
  \n
  The pressure altitude of this airfield is:'
  answers:
    a: '1,800 ft'
    b: '1,980 ft'
    c: '2,260 ft'
    d: '2,440 ft'
  points: 2
- number: 57
  question: 'Use the following data\n
  Airfield:\n
    Elevation: 1,890 ft\n
    Runways: 17/35 sealed TODA 3,000 metres (slope level)\n
    12/30 short grass TODA 1,000 metres (slope 1% down to SE)\n
  ATIS:\n
    Terminal Information Delta\n
    Runway 12\n
    Wind 150/15\n
    QNK 1,010
    Temperature 15\u00B0C\n
    Cloud: FEW 3000\n
    Runway wet.\n
    Works in progress Runway 17/35\n
  \n
  The density altitude of this airfield is:'
  answers:
    a: '1,800 ft'
    b: '1,980 ft'
    c: '2,260 ft'
    d: '2,460 ft'
  points: 2
- number: 58
  question: 'Use the following data\n
  Airfield:\n
    Elevation: 1,890 ft\n
    Runways: 17/35 sealed TODA 3,000 metres (slope level)\n
    12/30 short grass TODA 1,000 metres (slope 1% down to SE)\n
  ATIS:\n
    Terminal Information Delta\n
    Runway 12\n
    Wind 150/15\n
    QNK 1,010
    Temperature 15\u00B0C\n
    Cloud: FEW 3000\n
    Runway wet.\n
    Works in progress Runway 17/35\n
  \n
  The headwind component on the duty runway is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: '5 kt'
    b: '8 kt'
    c: '10 kt'
    d: '12 kt'
  points: 1
- number: 59
  question: 'Use the following data\n
  Airfield:\n
    Elevation: 1,890 ft\n
    Runways: 17/35 sealed TODA 3,000 metres (slope level)\n
    12/30 short grass TODA 1,000 metres (slope 1% down to SE)\n
  ATIS:\n
    Terminal Information Delta\n
    Runway 12\n
    Wind 150/15\n
    QNK 1,010
    Temperature 15\u00B0C\n
    Cloud: FEW 3000\n
    Runway wet.\n
    Works in progress Runway 17/35\n
  \n
  Use the Cessna take-off chart p376.\n
  At the MTOW, the take-off distance required on runway 12 is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: '550 m.'
    b: '730 m.'
    c: '890 m.'
    d: '980 m.'
  points: 3
- number: 60
  question: 'Use the following data\n
  Airfield:\n
    Elevation: 1,890 ft\n
    Runways: 17/35 sealed TODA 3,000 metres (slope level)\n
    12/30 short grass TODA 1,000 metres (slope 1% down to SE)\n
  ATIS:\n
    Terminal Information Delta\n
    Runway 12\n
    Wind 150/15\n
    QNK 1,010
    Temperature 15\u00B0C\n
    Cloud: FEW 3000\n
    Runway wet.\n
    Works in progress Runway 17/35\n
  \n
  Use the Piper Landing Chart p 383.\n
  Under the conditions given, the landing distance required for this aircraft 
  is closest to:'
  answers:
    a: '310 m.'
    b: '420 m.'
    c: '530 m.'
    d: '640 m.'
  points: 3
